Marge Champion Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Marge Champion Collection 1910-2006 (bulk 1940-1990)
ML31.C52
Champion, Marge
around 3,500 items 39 containers 34 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Marge Champion (b. 1919) is an American actress, dancer, director, choreographer, and teacher. The collection, which documents her life and career, includes biographical materials, correspondence, photographs, programs, promotional materials, manuscript music scores and parts, articles, business papers, clippings, scripts, scrapbooks, awards and posters. The collection also includes materials related to Champion's former husband, director and choreographer Gower Champion, and her father, dancer and choreographer Ernest Belcher.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Belcher, Ernest, 1883-1973.; Champion, Gower, 1919-1980--Correspondence.; Champion, Gower, 1919-1980--Photographs.; Champion, Gower, 1919-1980.; Champion, Marge--Archives.; Champion, Marge--Correspondence.; Champion, Marge--Photographs.; Champion, Marge.; Champion, Marge.; Sagal, Boris, 1923-1981.
Organizations
Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival.; Jacob's Pillow.; Mafundi Institute (Watts, Los Angeles, Calif.); Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer.; Sifriyah le-maḥol, Yiśraʼel.
Subjects
Actors--United States.; Choreographers--United States.; Dance in motion pictures, television, etc.--United States.; Dance--Production and direction.; Dance--United States.; Dancers--United States.; Motion pictures--United States.; Music--Manuscripts.; Musical films--United States.; Musicals--United States.; Performing arts--United States.; Popular music--United States.; Theater--United States.; Theatrical producers and directors--United States.; Women dancers--United States.
Titles
Hello Dolly!; Snow White and the seven dwarfs (Motion picture)
Form/Genre
Artifacts (Object genre); Awards.; Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographic prints.; Posters.; Programs (Documents); Promotional materials.; Scrapbooks.; Scripts (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Marge Champion, 2006. Additional items on Ernest Belcher were donated in 2012 by Naima Prevots.
Accruals
Further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Approximately forty moving images and sound recordings from the Marge Champion Collection have been transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. In addition, books that came with the collection have been transferred to the Music Division's general collections. An inventory of these materials is available in the Music Division's collection file, as well as in appendices "A" and "B" of a paper copy of the finding aid located in the Performing Arts Reading Room.
Other Repositories
Additional collections of interest include the Ernest Belcher Papers and Gower Champion Papers at the UCLA Library, Dept. of Special Collections, and the Popular Balanchine Dossiers at the New York Public Library.
Related Material
Related materials in the Library of Congress can be found in the
Alexander King Papers
in the Manuscript Division, as well as the
Bob Fosse and Gwen Verdon Collection
in the Music Division.
Access and Restrictions
The Marge Champion Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1919, Sept. 2 Born Marjorie Belcher, Los Angeles, California
1934 Modeled for Walt Disney's animated film Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs
1936 Stage debut at the Hollywood Bowl performing with Los Angeles Civic Opera
1937 Married Disney animator Art Babbitt (1907-1992) (divorced 1940)
1939 Starred in Universal film Honor of the West, directed by George Waggner Appeared as one of Irene’s girlfriends in the Astaire-Rogers film The Story of Vernon and Irene Castle Toured with the Three Stooges
1940 Modeled for Disney films Fantasia and Pinocchio
1942 Married television media personality Alexander King (1899-1965) (divorced circa 1945)
1943 Appeared on Broadway in Lerner and Loewe musical What’s Up, directed and choreographed by George Balanchine (some sources incorrectly list her name as “Marjorie Beecher”)
1945 Formed “Gower and Bell” with Gower Champion Starred on Broadway in the Richardson and Berney play Dark of the Moon (as the Fair Witch)
1946 Starred in Jerome Kern musical Sally at the Papermill Playhouse, New Jersey
1947 Married Gower Champion (1921-1980) (divorced 1973) Appeared on Broadway in Duke Ellington’s only musical, Beggar’s Holiday (billed as Marjorie Belle as The Lookout, The Girl, and the Lead Dancer)
1948-1950 Assistant to the choreographer (Gower Champion) for Broadway show Lend an Ear, starring Carol Channing
1949 Appeared in Dark of the Moon on television
1950 Marge and Gower appeared in Paramount film Mr. Music, with Bing Crosby
1951 Marge and Gower starred and danced in MGM musical film Show Boat, with Howard Keel and Kathryn Grayson
1952 Marge and Gower starred and danced in the MGM musical film Everything I Have is Yours Marge and Gower starred and danced in the MGM musical Lovely to Look At, remake of Astaire-Rogers film Roberta (featured Champions dancing in “Smoke Gets in Your Eyes” and dancing and singing in “I Won’t Dance”)
1953 Marge and Gower starred and danced in MGM musical film Give a Girl a Break, directed by Stanley Donen
1955 Marge and Gower starred and danced in MGM musical film Jupiter’s Darling Marge and Gower danced in Columbia Pictures film Three for the Show Marge and Gower starred on Broadway in 3 for Tonight, directed by Gower Champion Starred in CBS television special 3 for Tonight
1957 Marge and Gower appeared in episode of General Electric Theater television show entitled “Mischief at Bandy Leg” Marge and Gower Champion Show, a television situation comedy, premiered on CBS
1961 Starred in Invitation to March at La Jolla
1964 Starred in Everybody Out, the Castle is Sinking!, which never made it to Broadway (opened in Boston at the Colonial Theater)
1964-1970 Special assistant on Hello Dolly!, directed and choreographed by Gower Champion
1965 Starred in High Button Shoes, St. Louis Muny Opera
1965-1966 Prepared to star on Broadway in The Playroom (cannot verify that she actually appeared in the show)
1966 Starred in The Women, with Gloria Swanson and Julie Adams
1968 Appeared in MGM film The Party, directed by Blake Edwards Appeared in Columbia film The Swimmer, directed by Frank Perry
1969-1973 Involved in the Mafundi Institute where she had a dance floor installed
1970 Choreographed Jean Genet’s The Blacks for the Mafundi Institute (located in the Watts district of Los Angeles), directed by Ivan Dixon
1975 Dance supervisor for Paramount film The Day of the Locust, directed by John Schlesinger Choreographer for Columbia television film Queen of the Stardust Ballroom Won Emmy Award for Outstanding Achievement in Choreography for Queen of the Stardust Ballroom
1976 Appeared in That’s Entertainment, Part II, MGM film that presented “golden moments” from its film library. Marge and Gower Champion were represented by a clip from the 1952 MGM film Lovely to Look At
1977 Married television and film director Boris Sagal (1923-1981)
1978 Choreographer on three episodes of Warner Bros. television mini-series The Awakening Land Directed two-woman play Women and Other People
1980 Gower Champion died just hours before the Broadway opening of 42nd Street, which he was directing
1981 Champion’s husband, Boris Sagal, killed when he walked into the blades of a helicopter while on location
1982 Appeared as a ballet instructor in an episode of the television series Fame Directed RKO television movie I Do!, I Do! Host of Symphony in Three Movements television special honoring 100th anniversary of Igor Stravinsky’s birth
1983 Starred on Broadway in 5-6-7-8...Dance!
1985 Appeared in ABC television’s Night of 100 Stars II celebrity benefit for the Actors Fund of America Provided additional staging for Tonight at 8:30 at the Williamstown Theater Festival
1987 Marge and Gower’s son Blake Champion died at the age of 25 Marge donated Blake’s Barn to Jacob’s Pillow Dance Festival in his memory Choreographic associate for Broadway’s Stepping Out, directed and starring Tommy Tune Choreographer for Grover’s Corners, a musical version of Our Town, at the Marriott Theatre in Lincolnshire, Illinois
1988 Directed and choreographed Stepping Out at the Berkshire Theater Festival
1989 Directed Lute Song at the Berkshire Theater Festival
1990 Starred in No, No, Nanette at the St. Louis MUNY Opera Choreographed She Loves Me at the Berkshire Theater Festival
1991 Received the Legends of the Dance Award at Florida State’s Triple Crown Ballroom Dance Championship
1997 Received the Commonwealth Award from the state of Massachusetts
2001 Appeared in Broadway revival of Follies
2009 Inducted into National Museum of Dance's Hall of Fame, Saratoga, New York
Scope and Content Note
The Marge Champion Collection contains materials pertaining to Champion's life and career, and spans the period 1910-2006, with the bulk of the materials falling between 1940 and 1990.
Materials relating to Champion's former husband, Gower Champion, and to her father, Ernest Belcher, are significant and are woven throughout the collection. Gower Champion was a renowned dancer, director, and choreographer. Born in Illinois in 1919, and raised in Los Angeles, he began dance tours in 1933 with Jeanne Tyler. Documents pertaining to these tours are included in this collection. After World War II, he and Marge became dance partners and married in 1947. They performed primarily as a team throughout the 1950s, although Gower began to branch out, serving as a Broadway choreographer on Lend an Ear (1948) and Make a Wish (1951), and as choreographer and director on 3 for Tonight (1955). In the 1960s, Gower had a string of Broadway hits as choreographer and/or director, including Bye Bye Birdie (1960), Carnival! (1961), Hello Dolly! (1964), and I Do! I Do! (1966). These productions are documented in the collection through clippings, photographs, scrapbooks and written material. Gower and Marge Champion divorced in 1973. His shows from the late 1960s and 1970s include The Happy Time (1968), Prettybelle (1971), Sugar (1972), Irene (1973), Mack & Mabel (1974), Rockabye Hamlet (1976), and A Broadway Musical (1978). Gower Champion died of a rare form of blood cancer on August 25, 1980, six hours before the opening-night curtain of what would become one of his greatest Broadway hits, 42nd Street. These later Gower Champion productions are not documented in the collection. However, the collection does contain material related to the 2005 book Before the Parade Passes By: Gower Champion and the Glorious American Musical, by John Gilvey, which chronicles Gower Champion's life and work.
Marge Champion's father, Ernest Belcher, was a dancer and choreographer who worked as a trainer and coach for many stars in Hollywood. He was born in London in 1883 and was the principal dancer for the Alhambra Theatre from 1902 to 1909. He moved to Los Angeles in 1915 and founded the Celeste School of Dance in 1916. He was the first choreographer to present dance at the Hollywood Bowl, for which he worked from 1922 until 1936. His first work as a film dance director was in 1918 when he staged dances for D.W. Griffith's Broken Blossoms. He would go on to work with many silent film era directors, including Cecil B. DeMille, Mack Sennett, and Thomas H. Ince. Although many of the films he worked on have been lost, his work can be seen in A Small Town Idol (1921), The Phantom of the Opera (1925), Twinkletoes (1926), The Jazz Singer (1927), King of Kings (1927), Hollywood Revue (1929), General Crack (1930), The Little Princess (1939), and possibly The Hunchback of Notre Dame (1923). He trained and coached many film performers, including Mary Pickford, Pola Negri, Ramon Navarro, Nanette Fabray and Shirley Temple. Known as the “Father of Ballet” in Southern California, Ernest Belcher died on February 24, 1973, in Los Angeles. A significant amount of material in the collection relates to Ernest Belcher, particularly in the Photographs series. In addition, there is Belcher footage in the audiovisual material that has been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division.
The Marge Champion Collection is arranged into eight series. The Musical Theater and Plays, Films, and Television series contains materials that document the depth and breadth of Champion's long and varied career. It is broken down into four subseries: musical theater and plays, films, television and orchestrations, and is arranged alphabetically by title within each subseries. The series contains an extensive array of materials about Marge Champion's career both before her partnership with Gower, including materials related to her work as a model for the character of Snow White, and after, as well as materials relating to their work together. Materials include manuscript scores and parts, scripts, playbills, photographs, clippings and correspondence.
The Photographs series contains photographs of Marge and Gower in rehearsal as well as glamour shots of the pair. It also contains historical photographs related to Ernest Belcher's career as a dance director for films, and coach and trainer of film actors. Items include photographs of individuals related to dance and film, including Lina Basquette (Ernest Belcher's stepdaughter), Colleen Moore, Derelys Perdue, Ramon Novarro, Georgia Graves, Joyce Coles, Shirley Temple, Cecil B. DeMille, Vivien Fay, Alexandre Volinin and Lydia Kyasht, Harvey Karels, the Crane Twins, Marjorie and Maria Tallchief, Patsy Ruth Miller, and Victor Moore's wife Shirley. In addition, there are photographs of Mae Ross being trained for the MGM "art of skating" film, Margaret Westberg, "Blair and Dean" dance team, Alice Maison, Marie Prevost, Michael Brigarite, Lucile Iverson, Lois Moran, May McAvoy, Tula Belle and her sister Ebba Mona, Pola Negri, June Roper, Ruth St. Denis, Danish dancer Britta Petersen, and John Barrymore. There are also several photographs of the dance team “the Celestes,” which featured Belcher and his partner Dorothy Edwards. The series also includes a piece of film reel from The Phantom of the Opera, an Ernest Belcher "vaudeville" photograph from around 1910, a film list for Ernest Belcher from the UCLA archives (date unknown), a 1928 Hollywood Bowl program, photographs of the "Carnival of Venice" ballet, and many photographs of scenes from films, including General Crack, The Jazz Singer, A Small Town Idol, Twinkletoes, a film that includes Ebba Mona and her sister Tula Belle, Beau Brummel, and possibly The Hunchback of Notre Dame.
The Personal and Business Papers series includes personal materials related to Marge’s family members, including half-sister Lina Basquette, father Ernest Belcher, sons Blake and Gregg, and husbands Gower Champion and Boris Sagal. It also contains biographical documents and clippings, and items from her childhood. The business materials include church and liturgical dance records, contracts, correspondence and agreements.
The largest series in the collection, Subject Files, focuses on Marge Champion's travels, event and conference appearances, awards, her involvement in various projects and organizations, and items relating to individuals, including Agnes DeMille, Nanette Fabray, Martha Graham, Mary Martin and Nancy Reagan.
The Clippings and Written Materials series contains clippings that span Marge Champion's entire career. It also contains articles and press clippings that focus on Marge and Gower Champion.
The Scrapbooks series chiefly relates to Marge and Gower Champion's early career as a team. It also contains a significant number of scrapbooks centering on Hello Dolly!, and to a lesser extent on I Do! I Do! and Bye Bye Birdie. Materials include clippings, photographs, correspondence and programs.
The Ephemera and Awards series contains Ernest Belcher’s ballet shoes, Marge Champion’s awards, and Ernest Belcher’s megaphone from 1925 signed by many notable performers, including Sam Warner, John Barrymore, Harry Myers, Lina Basquette, Gloria Swanson, Derelys Perdue, Ramon Novarro, Dolores Costello, Sally Rand, Marion Davies, Pola Negri, and Colleen Moore.
The Posters series includes posters from MGM musicals and other films and theater engagements in which Marge Champion appeared.
Approximately forty moving images and sound recordings from the Marge Champion Collection have been transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. In addition, books that came with the collection have been transferred to the Music Division's general collections. An inventory of these materials is available in the Music Division's collection file, as well as in appendices "A" and "B" of a paper copy of the finding aid located in the Performing Arts Reading Room.
Organization of the Marge Champion Collection
The Marge Champion Collection is organized in eight series:
Musical Theater and Plays, Films, and Television
Photographs
Personal and Business Papers
Subject Files
Clippings and Written Materials
Scrapbooks
Posters
Ephemera and Awards
http://lccn.loc.gov/2012563809
Container List
- Musical Theater and Plays, Films and Television (Box 1-7, 22-27)
  Articles and reviews, clippings, correspondence, notes, photographs, programs, scores and scripts.
  Arranged alphabetically by title within each subseries.
  - Musical Theater and Plays (Box 1-7)
    - Beggar’s Holiday: clippings, playbill, article, review, correspondence and photographs (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Bye Bye Birdie: correspondence, conference presentation, thesis chapter, undated program from later production, articles, photocopied playbill and printed vocal soundtrack (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Carnival script, Photocopy; Contains Gower Champion’s notes. (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Dark of the Moon: clippings, printed script, playbill, correspondence and photographs (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Everybody Out, the Castle is Sinking: playbill, clippings and photographs (Box-folder 1/5)
    - 5-6-7-8 Dance: programs, clippings, notes and photographs (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Flea in Her Ear: clippings and photographs (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Follies: correspondence and photographs (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Follies: script with scores and an article (Box-folder 7/2)
    - 42nd Street: clippings, playbills, advertisements and photographs (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Gay Divorcee script (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Grover’s Corners (dance movement by Marge Champion): programs, printed notes on production, two stories and photographs (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Hello Dolly!: book, playbills, programs, clippings, cast list, correspondence and photographs (Box-folder 2/1-2)
    - High Button Shoes: programs, clippings and photographs (Box-folder 2/3)
    - I Do! I Do!: stage director’s guide and other materials, including a tab for each song (Box-folder 6/1-2)
    - I Do! I Do!: playbill, programs, correspondence, clippings, cast list and photographs (Box-folder 2/4)
    - I Do! I Do! published score (Box-folder 5/12)
    - I Do! I Do!: “profit part”: correspondence and program (Box-folder 2/5)
    - I Do! I Do! script, from Tom Jones (Box-folder 6/3)
    - I Do! I Do!: stage director’s guide from Tom Jones with correspondence and notes (Box-folder 5/13)
    - Invitation to March: clippings, correspondence, magazine and photographs (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Jubilee script (Box-folder 6/7)
    - Leave It to Me script (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Lend an Ear: 40th anniversary correspondence, play, playbill, program, articles and photographs (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Lute Song: book, programs, clippings, cast list, notes and script with notes, Includes information on Yung Yung Tsuai Dance Company, Nai-Ni Chen and Chen Yi. (Box-folder 2/8 and 6/4)
    - Make a Wish: playbill, correspondence and photographs (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Mr. Music photographs (Box-folder 3/1)
    - No, No, Nanette: program from a later production, contact sheet, correspondence, choreographic notes, general notes, printed scores, clippings, vocal score and photographs (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Out of this World script (Box-folder 6/8)
    - The Playroom clippings (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Sally: clippings, program and photographs (Box-folder 3/4)
    - She Loves Me: programs, notes on costumes, clippings, photographs and script (Box-folder 3/5 and 7/1)
    - Small Wonder: playbill, clippings, printed score and photographs (Box-folder 3/6)
    - “Stepping Out at Berkshire Theatre Festival”: program, correspondence with Richard Harris and clippings (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Stepping Out: programs and photographs (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Stepping Out notes (Box-folder 6/5 and 7/3)
    - Stepping Out, with Tommy Tune: correspondence and clippings (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Sugar: playbill and photographs (Box-folder 3/10)
    - 3 for Tonight: correspondence, playbill, clippings, program and photographs (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Tonight at 8:30 (Williamstown Theater Festival, 1985): program, scores, rehearsal call, and published plays by Noel Coward (Box-folder 3/12)
    - What’s Up: publicity material and photographs (Box-folder 3/13)
    - The Women: clippings, programs and photographs (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Women and Other People: script, program, correspondence, clippings, scores and notes (Box-folder 3/15)
    - Miscellaneous stage shows: clippings, playbills, programs and photographs (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Night club engagements: photographs, clippings, correspondence, menu and score book (Box-folder 3/16)
    - Publicity gimmicks: photographs and clippings (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Films (Box 4-5, 27)
    - Everything I Have is Yours photographs (Box-folder 4/12)
    - Girl Most Likely photographs (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Give a Girl a Break photographs (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Jupiter’s Darling: photographs and correspondence (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Lovely to Look At: correspondence, photographs and clippings (Box-folder 5/4)
    - The Party: clippings, photographs and transcript from TV appearance (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Showboat: photographs, reunion program, clippings, score and correspondence (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs: L’Illustration, 1938, A book with material on Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs. (Box-folder 27/1)
    - Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs: Materials on miscellaneous films, such as clippings and photographs, including Disney material (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs: article and cover photographs from Life magazine (Box-folder 27/4)
    - Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs materials, including photographs, articles, stamp, invitation to exhibit, correspondence, Pinocchio and Fantasia material, clippings, score, Willis Pyle letter, 50th anniversary production information and invitation, fan drawings (Box-folder 5/7)
    - The Swimmer: clippings and photographs (Box-folder 5/8)
    - That’s Entertainment, Part II: clippings, program and correspondence (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Three for the Show: correspondence, clippings and photographs (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Television (Box 4, 6)
    - CBS cable: correspondence, clippings, notes and booklet (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Fame: two photographs (Box-folder 4/8)
    - “Mischief at Bandy Leg” (episode from General Electric Theater) photographs (Box-folder 4/10)